# Fabio Miranda

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE, COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING

University of Illinois at Chicago

851 S. Morgan St, MC 152, Chicago, IL, 60607

□ (+1) 347-545-6405 | **Transport** fabiom@uic.edu | **A** fmiranda.me

## **Research Interests**

I am interested in developing techniques that allow for the interactive visual analysis of large-scale data, combining methods from visualization, data management, machine learning and computer graphics. I have worked closely with domain experts from different fields and the outcome of these collaborations included not only research published in leading venues, but also systems that were made available to experts in academia, industry and government agencies. My work has also received extensive coverage from different media outlets, including The New York Times, The Economist, Architectural Digest, Curbed, among others.

#### **Education**

2012 - 2018 Ph.D. in Computer Science

New York, NY, USA

New York University (NYU)

Advised by Professor Cláudio T. Silva, IEEE Fellow

Dissertation: "Data structures for the interactive visual analysis of urban data".

2009 - 2011 M.S. in Computer Science

Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Advised by Professor Waldemar Celes.

Thesis: "Volume rendering of unstructured hexahedral meshes".

2005 - 2009 B.S. in Computer Science

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG) Advised by Professor Luiz Chaimowicz.

## **Professional Experience**

Oct. 2020 - present University of Illinois at Chicago

Chicago, IL, USA

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering

Fall 2018 - Fall 2020 New York University

New York, NY, USA

Postdoctoral researcher

Summer 2016 Argonne National Laboratory

Lemont, IL, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Venkatram Vishwanath

Summer 2015 IBM T.J. Watson Research Center

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Bruce D'Amora

Summer 2014 AT&T Research

Middletown, NJ, USA

Research intern, Mentors: Lauro Lins and James Klosowski

Summer 2013 Sandia National Laboratories

Albuquerque, NM, USA

Research intern, Mentor: Patricia Crossno

2009 - 2012 **TecGraf / PUC-Rio** 

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research assistant, Mentor: Waldemar Celes

## **Awards**

2018 SIGMOD Best Demonstration Award

For "Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets Using Urbane".

2018 Pearl Brownstein Doctoral Research Award

For doctoral research that shows the greatest promise, awarded by NYU.

**CAPES and Petrobras Fellowships** 2010-2012 Awarded during M.S. studies. FINEP and CNPg Fellowships 2006-2009 Awarded during B.S. studies.

**Selected Media Coverage** 

Escuelas y comunidades latinas en Chicago son las más afectadas por la contaminación, según estudio February 2022

Univision Chicago 🗹

November 2017 Urban Pulse maps, analyzes use of urban spaces

GCN [7

Urban Pulse Uses Social Media Data to Show Cities in a New Light September 2017

Architectural Digest 🗷

September 2017 New program wants to improve cities with the power of tweets and Flickr uploads

Curbed 🗹

Mapping the Shadows of New York City: Every Building, Every Block December 2016

The New York Times 🗗

Listen to the music of the traffic in the city October 2016

The Economist 📝

## **Publications**

Underlined name: advised UIC student \*YYYY: paper submitted after joining UIC

#### **Under review:**

DeepShadow: City-Scale Automatic Shadow Detection using Building Height Information [J] \*2022 K. Omar, G. Moreira, D. Hodczak, M. Hosseini, M. Lage, F. Miranda IEEE Transactions on Big Data

Putting the Environment back in "Environmental Justice": A Two-Dimensional Approach for Area Identification [J] \*2022 M. Becerra, J. Liang, M. Siciliano, F. Fusi, F. Miranda, A. Sambanis, P. Boda, S. Derrible, M. Cailas Environmental Justice journal

Mapping the Walk: A Scalable Computer Vision Approach for Generating Sidewalk Network Datasets [J] \*2022 M. Hosseini, A. Sevtsuk, F. Miranda, R. M. Cesar Jr, C. T. Silva Computers, Environment and Urban Systems

## Accepted:

A Comparison of Spatiotemporal Visualizations for 3D Urban Analytics [C] \*2022 R. Mota, M. Horga, N. Ferreira, J. D. Silva, M. Lage, L. Ceferino, U. R. Alim, E. Sharlin, F. Miranda IEEE VIS 2022

Towards Global-Scale Crowd+AI Techniques to Map and Assess Sidewalks for People with Disabilities [C] \*2022 J. Froehlich, Y. Eisenberg, M. Hosseini, F. Miranda et al. The 24th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS '22)

A Comparative Study of Methods for Visualization of Probability Distributions of Geographical Data [J] \*2022 S. Srabanti, C. V. de Souza, E. J. da Silva, M. Lage, N. Ferreira, F. Miranda Multimodal Technologies and Interaction 6 (7), 53

[W] *2022	Towards Global-Scale Crowd+AI Techniques to Map and Assess Sidewalks for People with Disabilities M. Hosseini, M. Saugstad, <b>F. Miranda</b> , A. Sevtsuk, C. T. Silva, J. E. Froehlich <i>AVA: Accessibility, Vision, and Autonomy Meet (CVPR 2022 Workshop)</i>
[J] *2022	Near-fall detection in unexpected slips during over-ground locomotion S. Wang, <b>F. Miranda</b> , Y. Wang, <u>R. Rasheed</u> , T. Bhatt <i>Sensors</i>
[C] *2022	Urban Rhapsody: Large-scale Visual Exploration of Urban Soundscapes J. Rulff, <b>F. Miranda</b> , M. Hosseini, M. Lage, M. Cartwright, G. Dove, J. P. Bello, C. Silva  Computer Graphics Forum
[C] *2022	A Tale of Two Centers: Visual Exploration of Health Disparities in Cancer Care <u>S. Srabanti</u> , M. Tran, V. Achim, D. Fuller, G. Canahuate, <b>F. Miranda</b> , G.E. Marai  2022 IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis)
[J] *2022	CitySurfaces: City-scale Semantic Segmentation of Sidewalks Surfaces M. Hosseini, <b>F. Miranda</b> , J. Lin, C. Silva Sustainable Cities and Society
[J] *2022	Visualizing Simulation Ensembles of Extreme Weather Events C. V. de Souza, P. Luz, M. Cataldi, <b>F. Miranda</b> , M. Lage Computers & Graphics
[S] *2021	Visualizing Environmental Justice Issues in Urban Areas with a Community Input Approach J. Flax-Hatch, <u>S. Srabanti</u> , <b>F. Miranda</b> , A. Sambanis, M. Cailas  2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium  Featured on Univision Chicago
[S] *2021	Sidewalk Measurements from Satellite Images: Preliminary Findings M. Hosseini, I. B. Araujo, H. Yazdanpanah, E. Tokuda, <b>F. Miranda</b> , C. Silva, R. M. Cesar Jr 2nd Spatial Data Science Symposium
[W] *2021	COVID-19 EnsembleVis: Visual Analysis of County-level Ensemble Forecast Models <u>S. Srabanti</u> , G. E. Marai, <b>F. Miranda</b> 12th Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare
[W] *2021	Transportation Scenario Planning with Graph Neural Network A. A. Peregrino, <u>S. Pradhan</u> , Z. Liu, N. Ferreira, <b>F. Miranda</b> 10th International Workshop on Urban Computing
[J] 2021	UrbanRama: Navigating Cities in Virtual Reality S. Chen, <b>F. Miranda</b> , N. Ferreira, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Brenner, C. Defanti, M. Koutsoubis, L. Wilson, K. Perlin, C. Silva <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (accepted)</i>
[C] 2020	Urban Mosaic: Visual Exploration of Streetscapes Using Large-scale Image Data <b>F. Miranda</b> , M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, M. Hosseini, G. Dove, C. T. Silva  2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.
[C] 2020	Learning Geo-Contextual Embeddings for Commuting Flow Prediction  Z. Liu, <b>F. Miranda</b> , W. Xiong, J. Yang, Q. Wang, C. T. Silva  Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence.
[J] 2019	Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time <b>F. Miranda</b> , H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 3, pp. 1559-1574, Mar 2019.</i> <b>Featured on The New York Times</b>

	<b>F. Miranda</b> , M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Mydlarz, J. Salamon, Y. Lockerman, J. <i>Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 37, no. 3, pp. 23-35, Jun 2018.</i>	riene, er n enta	
[C] 2018	Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets using Urban	ne	
	H. Doraiswamy, E. Tzirita Zacharatou, <b>F. Miranda</b> , M. Lage, A. Ailamaki, C. T. Si	lva, J. Freire	
	2018 ACM SIGMOD Intl. Conf. on Management of Data - Demo.  Best Demonstration Award		
[J] 2018	Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Analysis: A Visual Analytics Perspective		
[3] 2016	H. Doraiswamy, J. Freire, M. Lage, <b>F. Miranda</b> , C. T. Silva		
	IEEE Computer Graphics and Application, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 26-35, Sept/Oct 2018.		
[J] 2018	TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotempor	ral Datasets	
	F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva		
	IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 13	394-1407, Mar 2018.	
[J] 2017	Urban Pulse: Capturing the Rhythm of Cities	C T C'I	
	<b>F. Miranda</b> , H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, K. Zao, B. Goncalves, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 23, no. 1, pp. 75</i>		
	Featured on The Economist, invited to SIGGRAPH 2017 TVCG special session		
[C] 2017	Data Visualization Tool for Monitoring Transit Operation and Performance		
	A. Kurkcu, <b>F. Miranda</b> , K. Ozbay, C. T. Silva		
	5th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Models and Technologies for Intelligent Transportation Systems (2017).		
[W] 2016	TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets		
	<b>F. Miranda</b> , L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva  Data Systems for Interactive Analysis (DSIA) 2016.		
[J] 2012	Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes		
[3] 2012	F. Miranda, and W. Celes		
	The Visual Computer Journal, vol. 28, no. 10, pp. 1005-1014, Oct 2012.		
[C] 2011	Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes		
	F. Miranda, and W. Celes		
	24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).		
[C] 2011			
	A. Rocha, <b>F. Miranda</b> , and W. Celes 24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).		
	2 it is obligation of the control of		
	Funding		
	Data readiness for 'Perturbation training for enhancing	National Institute of	
Fall 2022 - Fall 2023	stability and limb support control for fall-risk reduction among stroke survivors'	Health	
	Co-I, \$300,000 (total)		
	PI: Tanvi Bhatt (UIC)		
Fall 2022 - Fall 2023	PRESUR: Planning a Resilient and Equitable State Using	Discovery Partners	
Tall 2022 - Tall 2023	Real-time Data	Institute	
	Co-PI, \$125,000 (direct total)		
	PI: Sybil Derrible (UIC)		

## **Teaching**

Spring 2022 CS425: Computer Graphics I

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Undergraduate course. No. of students enrolled: 49. Average student evaluation score: 4.08 / 5.0 (n=37)

Course page 🗹

Fall 2021 **CS594: Big Data Visualization & Analytics** 

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Graduate course. No. of students enrolled: 29. Average student evaluation score: 4.4 / 5.0 (n=25) Course page ☑

Spring 2021 CS425: Computer Graphics I

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Undergraduate course. No. of students enrolled: 41. Average student evaluation score: 4.03 / 5.0 (n=33) Course page ☑

**Advised Students** 

2021 - Ph.D. students (advisor)

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Gustavo Moreira, Kazi Omar, Marius Horga, Sanjana Srabanti (co-adivising with G. Elisabeta Marai)

2021 - M.Sc. students (advisor)

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Davide Bartoletti, Soham Pradhan

2021 - Undergraduate students (advisor)

University of Illinois at

Chicago

Daniel Hodczak, Jayanth Podapati, Reem Sheikh, Rahiya Rasheed

2018 - Ph.D. students (mentor)

**New York University** 

Zhicheng Liu (CS PhD student at Southeast University, China), Maryam Hosseini (Urban Systems PhD student at Rutgers), Shaoyu Chen (CS PhD student at NYU), João Rulff (CS PhD student at NYU).

**Selected Invited Talks and Presentations** 

July 2022 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Immersive Analytics

**Opportunities** 

Davis, California, USA

Kavli Frontiers of Science Symposium

National Academy of Science

April 2022 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Immersive Analytics

**Opportunities** 

Online

The Next Evolution: XR & AEC

VRAR CHICAGO

January 2022 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland

Online

Urban Initiative Program New York University

April 2021 Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland

Online

Department of Energy Computer Graphics Forum 2021

Department of Energy

Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational April 2021 Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil **Perspective on Cities** Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational March 2021 Niteroi, RJ, Brazil **Perspective on Cities** Fluminense Federal University December 2018 **Exploration of Street-Level Images at Scale** New York City, NY, USA Pedestrian Movement Technology Showcase at Metro North **Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale** November 2018 Berlin, Germany **Shadows over Time** IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS) Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual June 2018 Brno, Czech Republic **Analysis of Large Time Series** EG/VGTC Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2017 Phoenix, AZ, USA **Spatiotemporal Datasets** IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS) September 2016 **Visualizing and Exploring Urban Data** Boston, MA, USA **Data Visualization Summit** TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2016 Chicago, IL, USA **Spatiotemporal Datasets** Data Systems for Interactive Analysis Workshop (DSIA)

## **Academic Services**

## **Program chair**

• SIBGRAPI (2022)

## Conference and workshop organization

- 1st Workshop on The Future of Urban Accessibility at ASSETS'22
- VIS 2021, Local co-chair (2021)
- The Future of Global-Scale Spatial Data Collection and Analyses on Urban (in)Accessibility for People with Disabilities Workshop, Co-chair (2021)

## **Program committees**

- IEEE VIS Full papers (2022) IEEE VIS Short papers (2019, 2020, 2021)
- EuroVis (2022) Visualization and Data Analysis Conference (2022) SIBGRAPI (2019, 2020, 2021)

#### **Editor**

• Computers & Graphics (SIBGRAPI 2022 Special Issue)

#### **Grant reviewer**

- NSF reviewer (GRFP, 2022), (CSSI, 2022)
- Center for Transportation, Equity, Decisions and Dollars reviewer (2022) Discovery Partners Institute reviewer (2021)

#### Journal reviewer

- IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics (2020, 2021) IEEE Trans. on Big Data (2020)
- IEEE Trans. on Intelligent Transportation Systems (2021) The Visual Computer Journal (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022) Transportation Research Record Journal (2020) International Journal of Geo-Information (2021)

#### **Conference reviewer**

- IEEE VIS (2020, 2021, 2022) EuroVis (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022) Sibgrapi (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022)
- VLDB (2021) WWW (2021) International Conference on Pattern Recognition (2020, 2021, 2022)

# **University Services**

## **Department committees**

- Faculty Search Committee (2021-2022, 2022-2023)
- Graduate Admission Committee (2020, 2021)

## Reviewer

• Provost's Graduate Research Award reviewer (2020)

#### **WCP** committees

• Carla Floricel (2021) • Md Nafiul Alam Nipu (2021) • Andrew Wentzel (2021) • Muhammad Abdul Wahhab (2021)

## **Master's project committees**

●Parikshit Solunke (2021) ● Pavana Doddi (2021)

# **Professional Memberships**

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM). Brazilian Computer Society (Sociedade Brasileira de Computação, SBC).